[Music]
Doo doo doo doo doo doo doo doo doo doo
doo.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
I still don't think it was a good idea
because what he did was a car to the
statute which is there's a Burman
amendment which basically says despite
these sanctions the first amendments
even if he went and he lost I thought
there was still a good argument on
appeal This shouldn't be a crime to
begin with because what he did was
constitutional protective activity US
citizen to be able to speak whatever he
wants to speak about.
There's no transfer of knowledge.
>> That's exactly right.
>> So, but
thankfully he's out now. He finished his
sentence. I was able to actually get his
sentence reduced by about seven months
and DOJ,
you know. Yeah. Because there were new
sentencing guidelines that came out. He
was very
>> Thank you so much. And they always say
This was a very grave crime.
>> No, it wasn't with General Flynn. Very
grave crime.
>> Exactly.
>> What are you talking about?
>> Hey. Hey.
Yeah. Gotcha.
Okay. Okay. Gotcha. Yep. Bye. Bye. Bye.
>> Okay. Very good. Um, so we can start.
>> Okay. Step aside.
>> All right. But we're going to start here
in about uh 15 20 seconds. So if anybody
wants to get situated, turn your phones
off. Get ready for another very
interesting tale here.
All right.
Okay. Let's get going here. This is, I
think, the third hour of what's going to
be an incredibly interesting programming
here at Hope. And how is hope going for
all of you? All right. Still good.
Last two hours I thought were pretty
pretty damn riveting. So yeah, you
you've got some big shoes to fill here,
John. And so u allow me to introduce
John Kuryaku. John uh may be known to
many of you, but for those of you to
whom he is not, John was a former high
ranking officer within CIA.
He was a counterterrorism officer and he
was the first US official to confirm CIA
torture of detainees. He was punished
for being a whistleblower. He served
nearly two years in federal prison. He
also exposed CIA's role in secret
rendition and torture of a Canadian
citizen Mahar in Syria. Since his
release, he's become a leading advocate
for transparency, for civil liberties,
and for whistleblower protections. He's
the author of several books. He
regularly speaks on topics related to
surveillance, intelligence overreach,
and ethics with respect to national
security. John co-ees cyber security and
anti-surveillance seminars with the Yale
Privacy Lob Lab founder Shawn O'Brien
and continues to challenge the culture
of secrecy and unaccountable power in
the intelligence community. So, let's
hear it for John Kuryako.
[Applause]
Thanks everybody. I'm going to give what
I think is probably um a presentation
not in the mainstream of what you've
been hearing yesterday and today. Uh but
I hope that I'm able to impart something
that's helpful. So I'm going to go back
to September 11th, 2001. I was uh I was
working in CIA headquarters as a
counterterrorism operations officer. The
job of a of an operations officer, very
simply, is to recruit spies to steal
secrets so that CIA analysts can analyze
those secrets and provide the policy
maker with the best informed blah blah
blah blah. Um, counterterrorism is is
different. Your job is to
well, before 911, your job was to
infiltrate terrorist groups. Post 911,
it was to capture, kill, infil in
infiltrate, disrupt, whatever.
everything changed, but we can get to
that in a few minutes. So, like
everybody else in the building on
September 11th, I volunteered to go to
Afghanistan or wherever to do whatever
was needed. And I I wasn't I wasn't
taken up on my offer. I was one of only
a handful of people, 16 in the entire
CIA, who was fluent in Arabic. And I
kept volunteering over and over. You got
to send me to Afghanistan. Surely you
need translators to to interrogate these
prisoners you're capturing. Well, it
turned out they weren't interrogating
anybody. They were shooting them. And so
they didn't need translators. There was
nothing to translate. Finally, I
complained so many times that the
director of the counterterrorist center
sent me to Pakistan as the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations.
And the first thing that I was told on
my first day was to come up with a
standard operating procedure for taking
down a terrorist safe house. I had had
all the operational training. I had had
the very specific counterterrorism
training and the driving and the
surveillance and the jumping out of
planes and all that stuff. Not much at
all in the way of tech.
So, I literally went back to my office
with a legal pad
and I thought to myself, what would I
need to do to take down a terrorist safe
house? Well, I would want it to be dark.
So, I wrote 0200 at the top of the paper
and I would need battering rams and guns
and ammunition and bulletproof vests and
secure comms and a satellite dish and
encrypted walkie-talkies. I just went to
galls.com. Galls.com.
It's a big police supply house in
Kentucky. I just ordered everything on
the on my CIA credit card and just had
it shipped out. So, when the stuff
arrived, we got a tip for a terrorist
safe house
because 9/11 was an an active criminal
investigation. We had to invite the FBI
as much as we hated to. and uh and it is
Pakistan, so we had to invite the
Pakistanis since it's their country. And
uh we took a battering ram and we broke
down the door and we caught these two
18-year-old kids. They both burst into
tears and one asked if he could call his
mom.
And I said to a colleague, "This is the
fearsome al-Qaeda.
This is what we're so afraid of. Their
children crying and asking if he can
call his mom." Well, maybe it was an
anomaly. And we did another one a week
later. We did another one a week after
that. Then we started doing two a week.
Sometimes occasionally we would do two a
night. After about six weeks,
I got a call on a Friday morning.
Friday and Saturday were the weekend in
Pakistan. And Friday was like the only
day of the week I allowed myself the
luxury of sleeping until 8:00. And so
the station chief woke me up and said,
"Come in immediately. something
important has come up. I speed into the
uh into the station and um it's
everybody. It's the station chief, the
deputy chief, the head of the FBI
contingent, his deputy and me. And the
chief says,
uh, we got a cable overnight from a
sister agency in Maryland that said that
Abu Zubeda was somewhere in Pakistan and
we had to catch him.
And everybody's kind of nodding and they
look at me and I'm thinking I'm, you
know, I'm nodding back and I'm thinking,
but I know that name from somewhere, but
I just can't place it. Well, we had been
told that Abu Zubeda was the number
three in al-Qaeda. That turned out to
not be true. He was a bad man. He was a
facilitator for al-Qaeda. He uh was kind
of a logistics guy. He created the House
of Martyrs, the the al-Qaeda safe house
in Peshawar, Pakistan. He had founded
and staffed al-Qaeda's two training
camps in Kandahar province in
Afghanistan and in Helman province also
in southern Afghanistan. And if you if
you wanted to make jihad, he would get
you into Afghanistan. If you were in
Afghanistan and and were tired of the
fight and wanted to go home, he would
get you out. He'd get you a passport and
a ticket home and take care of those
logistics. But he had never pledged
filty to Osama bin Laden. Never. He was
an independent player and he had
certainly never joined al-Qaeda. But
anyway, we didn't know that at the time.
We thought he was the number three. And
so the order is he's literally somewhere
in Pakistan
and you have to catch him. And I said,
"Guys, there are 220 million people in
this country. It's the size of Texas.
What do you mean he's somewhere in
Afghan or in Pakistan?" Well, that's
what you're here for.
I came up with a couple of low tech, no
tech ideas that were terrible.
For example, we were getting these these
little pings of information. He's in
Lahore. He's in Fiselabad. He's in
Lahore again. He went to Queta. This is
like every day.
And I said one day,
when I was a freshman in college,
my dad through our crooked state senator
got me a job for the summer as a toll
collector on the Pennsylvania Turnpike.
And there's a turnpike that collects
that connects Lahore with Fisal Labad. I
said, "I bet you I know how to run the
machine, the toll machine." I said, 'Why
don't we take all the Pakistanis out of
the booths, we staff the turnpike with
CIA guys, and when we see him, we grab
him. We're all heroes.
That was a terrible idea. There are like
50,000 people a day that go through
those those lanes. That was a dumb idea.
It didn't We wasted a week doing that.
So then I said, uh, I said, you know, we
need tech. We don't have any tech. So we
got these two tech officers from the CIA
from the Director of Science and
Technology
and they flew out to Islamabad and I
said look we have a a VIP that we need
to capture. Even his name was so highly
classified. We didn't even tell the
Pakistanis who we were after. We we
called him a big fish and then that
became Mr. Fish. And so they were they
would ask about you know what are we
doing about Mr. Fish today? So I said we
got this big fish and uh we we don't
know where he is. He he's moving around
constantly on the on the run. He knows
we're after him. He's a day ahead of us.
In some cases, he was an hour ahead of
us. We we broke into one safe house one
one day and there was still a lit
cigarette on the table and half an eaten
sandwich and he was gone. Some sometimes
we were like two or three days behind
him, but we were we were on the trail.
And I said, "Surely you guys must be
able to come up with with something that
can help us."
Well, we had his cell phone number. And
so I gave the cell phone number to these
two guys and they went down into the
bazaar and they bought, you know, a
couple of pieces of wood and some wires
and a soldering iron and I I don't know
what the heck they were buying down
there, but they came up with this thing.
They called it the magic box. And it had
a little telephone keypad in it. and we
punched in the number, his number, and
we just sat there. And they put it, they
installed just a little speaker.
So I said, "Well, what do we do?" They
said, "We wait till he turns the phone
on." Sure enough, about 12 hours later,
and yes, we're sitting there for 12
hours staring at each other.
He turns the phone on and makes a call
and the magic box starts to ping and
they say, "He's in that direction." and
we all jump up and we're like putting on
our strapping on our guns and all this
stuff and then it he shuts the phone
off. We couldn't even get out of the
office, let alone get in the car and
follow him through this city of 18
million people to try to figure out
where he is.
Finally, I said to my boss, um, this
isn't going to work there. There's
literally nothing that I know how to do
that's going to result in us locating
him. I said, 'I have a friend though at
headquarters. He's a targeting analyst
and uh I'd like to fly him out. So, I
cabled my friend. I said, 'Hey, can you
come to Islamabad? Like immediately,
like on the first flight. And sure
enough, 4:00 a.m. he arrived at the
airport. I picked him up and he said,
"So, what's what's the fire?" And I
said, "VIP that we're going after, the
orders came from the president that we
had to catch him. This isn't something
that we jinned up in the office. The
president specifically said, "I want you
to catch him." And we had not caught uh
a high level al-Qaeda fighter up to that
point. We had killed Muhammad Af uh when
we bombed Tora Bora the previous
October, but we didn't know where Bin
Laden or Amaz
was the closest we had come to anybody.
So,
we went back to the station and he took
a piece of butcher block paper about
this big. It was almost the size of a
small American uh billboard and he wrote
Abuza's phone number in the middle and
put a circle around it. And then around
that circle he wrote
the the names, the phone numbers, the
email addresses, the physical addresses
of everybody that had been in touch with
that number. And then he did it as a
secondary layer and then finally a
tertiary layer. took weeks to do this,
but in the end it looked like a work of
art. It looked pretty like a spiderweb
or something you'd see in a beautiful
mind. Remember when he has all the
strings pointing all these different
directions cuz he was insane. So, um,
the reason I asked this friend of mine
was specifically because he was a
targeting analyst. There are two
different kinds of analysts at the CIA.
There are intelligence analysts who read
all source intelligence, read all the
papers, think the big thoughts, write
papers that nobody's going to read, and
you know, become experts on a a
geographic area or on a on a a core um
issue like, you know, counterp
proliferation or something. Targeting
analysts are completely and totally
different. Targeting analysts
are almost exclusively assigned to the
directorate of operations and even then
specifically to the counterterrorism
center so that they can pour through
millions of pieces of data
much of it metadata in order to locate a
person. So why would you locate a
person? For only two reasons to kill
them or to capture them. That's it. or
to kidnap them and send them to
somewhere else where they can be
tortured and the US can deny that any
such thing is ever happening.
So
it took him several weeks and finally he
came to me and he said uh I I can't get
it down to any fewer than 14 sites. I
said 14 sites man three weeks you've
been working on this? We've never hit
more than two sites in a night. We don't
have personnel to to hit 14 sites
simultaneously. It's never been done
before. He said, "I'm sorry. I can't do
it. I can't get it any to any fewer than
14."
So, I I cabled CIA headquarters and I
said, "Um,
I need a a plane. I need 36 people, half
CIA, half FBI. We need pallets of
weapons and ammunition and night vision
goggles and battering rams and and
bulletproof vests and all this crap. 24
hours later, it's landing at the airport
in Lahore. And um
the larger stations that the CIA has
around the world have what are called
cash rooms. And they're literally small
rooms that are stacked to the ceiling
with cash.
50 million, 100 million, whatever you
happen to need. You just take what you
need, you sign it out, and you go do
your thing. So I said to the station
chief, I need I need $2 million in cash
like right now. And he said, 'Okay,
count it out. But I was warned my very
first week of the CIA, don't ever [__]
with finance, security, or medical.
Those three cannot just ruin your
career, they can send you to prison. So
every single dollar has to be accounted
for. So, I took $2 million. Buddy of
mine counted it. So, we had the count
right and we put it in duffel bags and
we drove to uh we requisitioned a van
from the motorpool and we drove to L'ore
and I went to see the Pakistani
intelligence service colonel that was in
charge of the city and he said, "What do
you need? What can I be helpful for
helpful on?" And I said, "I need a real
estate agent." He said, "Uh, well, what
are you going to do with that?" I said,
"I need to buy two safe houses, one in
in Lahore and one in Fiselabad." So, we
got this real estate agent and I said,
"I want to find the the biggest house
you can get us." He got us a 10-bedroom,
10b house, and we're thinking we can use
each bedroom for interrogations. I
bought it on the spot, paid cash, went
to Fiselabad, found a seven-bedroom
house there, bought that, paid cash, and
um and then we loaded all of our
equipment and our guns and stuff into
the into the two safe houses. So,
finally, and this is late March of 2002,
I I called a couple of my colleagues
together. We've got three dozen people
now, plus another four dozen Pakistanis.
And I said, I think we're ready to go.
We know where all 14 sites are. There's
no sense in pussy-footing around. Again,
there's no tech, right? Just what the
the targeting analyst did. And it was
just little bits and pieces like, "Oh,
here's an email. Oh, here's a cell phone
number." And he's just he's just
bringing them together. So, um, I said
the first thing we should do, I think,
is to drive around during the day and
make sure that we're not being set up. I
don't want to drive into an ambush. We
want to make sure there's ingress and
egress. If we get in to a neighborhood
and they trap us in, are we going to be
able to shoot our way out? So, we
started going from site one to site 14.
One thing we found right away in Lahore
was site 14 was a shish kebab stand with
a pay phone. So that is not helpful.
They the shish kebab stand closes at
midnight. Obviously there are al-qaeda
people living in the neighborhood.
They're using that pay phone. You can't
raid the shish kebab stand. So we cut it
off. So 13 sites.
One was a girl school which kind of
surprised us and and we ate crow on that
one. just to get that little detail out
of the way. We we broke the door down
that night and grabbed an 80-year-old
man and his three sons only to realize
that there were al-Qaeda people in the
neighborhood. He was the only guy in the
neighborhood who had a telephone and so
they would give him, you know, a couple
of rupees and they would make a call.
Well, here they're calling like Osama
bin Laden, right? So,
so we let him go and I had to make this
big scene. And I said, "Sir, on behalf
of the president of the United States,
I'm so sorry that we broke down your
door. I'm so sorry that we raised our
voices in the presence of your wife and
your daughters, we would like to uh, you
know, repair the door." And the
Pakistani colonel said to me, you should
offer to buy them shoes. They didn't
have any shoes. So I said, "As a gift
from the people of the United States, I
would like to buy shoes for you and your
family and the girls that are in your
school." The next day, the guy's on TV.
He says, "The Americans broke into my
house at 2:00 in the morning. They
shattered my door, but they were very
nice and they bought us shoes and they
gave us food,
so it was okay." So, so we're driving
around now. So, we ended up with with
two of these sites being in Lore and 11
of them being in Fiselabad.
Almost all of them were just mud huts,
corrugated tin roofs or made out of
concrete block. There was really nothing
to them. And it was clear from early on
there was no there was no problem that
we were going to run into where we would
be ambushed.
And so
as we're driving around, I got a call
from the targeting analyst who remained
behind in um Islamabad and he said,
"Listen, I just got a call from a
friendly Western intelligence service
and they had a walk-in." Now, a walk-in
is someone who literally walks into an
embassy and says, "I have information
that I want to pass to an intelligence
officer." 95%, these are actual numbers,
95% of them are either lunatics or
liars.
Some are what are called intelligence
peddlers where they actually do have a
little nugget of interesting information
and they'll give it to you, but they
want $100 or $200. happy to happy to
give you the $100. But then they're
going to go to the British embassy and
sell it to them and the French embassy
and the Russians and the Chinese and
that's a month's salary. That's a good
life
for something you picked up at the
coffee house. Um there are some that are
probes. Like you'll get an Iranian
coming in saying, "I'd like to talk to a
CIA officer." And then they're like
looking to see where the cameras are,
how thick the windows are, who's armed,
you know, how many people are wearing
disguises or not wearing disguises.
They're they're probing just in case
they need to attack our embassy someday.
They want to try to find a
vulnerability.
But then there's 1% that's the real
McCoy.
So, the analyst said, "The walk-in told
our allies that there's a large group of
al-Qaeda fighters and they're hiding in
a big yellow house."
I said, "I want to talk to the walk-in."
He said, "Can't do it. I already asked.
They said the walk-in's not available."
I said, "That's ridiculous. If it's a
walk-in, the walk-in's always
available." Which told me that there was
no walk-in. It was an intercept. And
they didn't want to share with us that
they were on
phones.
I said fine. I took that call just as we
were passing through from the front gate
to the back gate of the University of
Fisa Labad. And as we came out the back
gate, what was there but a gigantic
yellow house? And I said, "That's the
house. It has to be the house." And the
Pakistani uh colonel said,"I can tell
you right now something bad is happening
in that house." What? I said, he said,
"Look, it's got to be 105 degrees right
now and all of the shutters are closed.
They have to be broiling in there, but
the shutters are closed so as not to
attract attention." I said, "Well, we'll
put a bigger team on that house." We
ended up catching 27 people in that
house crammed in like sardines.
But anyway, there was one final
site that we needed to get to.
And as we're
trying to negotiate the traffic to get
there, the analyst calls back and he
said, "Abu Zubeta just made a terrible
mistake." I said, "What was it?" He said
he accessed his Hotmail account with a
landline. I said, "Oh my god, tell me
you have an address for the landline."
And he gave me the address and it was
the final site. And I said, "We I still
have chills." This was 23 years ago. I
still get chills when I think about it.
I said, "We got him."
And so we drive over to the site and
it's an empty field.
Not just that there's not a house on it.
There's never been a house on it ever.
And I said to the Pakistani, "How can
this be? We're sure that the call came
from this site." And he laughed and he
said, "You've never lived in Pakistan
before. This is quite common." He said,
"When land is legally divided into lots,
each lot is assigned a landline.
But poor people will climb a telephone
pole, splice a wire, and run a new wire
to their house so that they can make
long-distance calls. And the bill goes
to the guy who owns the plot.
I said, "That's pretty smart, actually."
So he called one of his tech officers
who comes, climbs the telephone pole,
goes through this Medusa's head of wires
up there, finds the one wire, literally
follows it down the pole like this, and
we're following down him down the alley,
and he says, "It's that house right
there."
So that night at 10 o'clock, we were at
the the bigger of the two safe houses in
uh Lahore and I I stood on the coffee
table and I said, "Guys, at the risk of
being melodramatic, we're going to have
to synchronize our watches like in the
movies." But I said, "Here's the plan.
0130,
you leave the safe house. 0145 be in the
neighborhood of the target. 0155
be within line of sight of the target.
0158. Get out of your car and exactly as
the clock strikes two, break down the
door, grab all the men, separate the
women and children from them, and then
we put all the men in patty wagons.
So that night,
I went to the roof of the Fisal Labad
safe house with one of my CIA
colleagues, and I remember looking at my
watch and saying, "O200, here we go."
And as soon as I said it, we could hear
this sound, this boink boink, like metal
on metal. And I said, "That's not good."
First of all, nobody is awake in
Fiselabad, Pakistan at 2:00 in the
morning. It doesn't matter if there are
7 million people there, the whole place
is sleeping. So this sound is not
normal.
And as soon as I said that, that's not
good, we heard shots fired. Well, we
knew that site 13 was the closest to the
safe house. So, I got on the radio. Rule
number one of of CIA operations, the
batteries never work. I I actually had
to go to NSA when I got back and I said,
they were like, "What can we do to be
more helpful in future operations?" I
said, "My god, we put a man on the moon.
We can't have a battery that lasts more
than 15 minutes." Like the battery,
every single operation, the battery
dies.
So, I called him on the phone. I said,
"What's going on over and he screams,
"Shots fired. Shots fired." I said, "I
know. That's why I'm calling you. Who's
firing at at whom?"
So, I couldn't understand what he was
saying. We ran downstairs. We we jumped
in the car and uh and sped over to the
site and it was it was chaos.
So, there were a dozen or so fighters on
the first floor of this house. Um, on
the second floor
there there was a there was a steel
reinforced door leading to the sec
second floor. The guys on the first
floor didn't know who was on the second
floor. They knew it was a VIP because
they had their own cook. And the door
was always locked. And every day the
cook would come downstairs, go to the
market, buy food, and go back upstairs
and cook. And they were never allowed to
see who was up there. Well, it was Abu
Zubeda, his Tunisian bodyguard,
and um an Assyrian bomb maker. When we
started breaking down the door, they ran
to the roof of the house and started to
jump to the roof of the neighboring
house to escape. Now, literally the last
thing I said when we were kicking off
from the original safe house was the
orders are to take them alive.
Nobody should fire their gun unless
they're being fired at, right? Everybody
understands. And everybody's like, "Yes,
the Pakistanis." Yes, yes, we
understand.
The Pakistani guy just starts picking
them off with an AK-47 from the street.
He killed the bomber with one shot. He
was dead before he hit the ground.
The second guy that jumped was uh the uh
the bodyguard and he was shot through
the femur, right through the center of
his femur. Abu Zuba was shot in the
thigh, the groin, and the stomach and um
and just dropped. So I get there and
like I said, it's chaos. And I said I
said, "What's going on?" And the
Pakistani says to me, "We got him. We
got your man." I said, "Who is he? Which
one is he? He's this one. And I'm
looking at him. I said, "That doesn't
look anything at all like Abazuba." We
had a six-year-old passport photo that
we doctorred nine ways from Sunday with
a baseball hat, glasses,
cowboy hat, beard and mustache. We had
hundreds of these variations. None of
them looked like him. The the passport
photo was this young, goodlooking. I
think he was like 21 in the photo.
Good-looking, thin guy with a a very
wellcropped beard and mustache. This guy
on the ground, fat, clean shaven, Albert
Einstein hair going all over the place.
I said that I I don't know who that is.
So I called the analyst. I said,
"Listen, the pack shot this guy and
they're saying it's him and I don't
think it's him. What should I do?"
He said, "Get me a picture of his of his
eye. I'll run a retinal scan." So, I
knelt down. Remember, phones didn't have
cameras in 2002. So, I had a camera
that, you know, cutting edge technology.
I could plug into the phone. And um
I knelt down and I shouted at him, "If
the hayun, open your eyes."
He was dying. He was bleeding to death.
So, I held his eyelids open, but his
eyes were rolled back. And I told the
analyst, "He's he's bleeding to death. I
can't even get him to show me his eyes."
And he told me, "Give me a picture of
his ear." I didn't know until that night
that no two people on Earth have the
same ears. They're like fingerprints.
So, I took a picture of his ear. I
plugged it into the uh phone, sent the
picture to Islamabad. He sent it to
Langley. Langley came back a minute
later and they said, "It's him."
So, we pick him up, we throw him into
the back of a filthy Toyota pickup
truck, and we rush him to uh the worst
place on earth, Fisabad Hospital. The
doctors there tried very quickly to
patch him up, but word got around the
al-Qaeda community that we had gotten
him. And so, they started driving by the
hospital and just opening fire on the
hospital. And we kept having to duck
down. And I said to Colonel Muhammad,
the Pakistani, I said, "If they realize
how lightly armed we are, we're dead.
Can we get a can we get a helicopter in
here?" And he said, "I think so." So 20
minutes later, the helicopter lands. I
walk into the operating room just like
this. I said, "Doc, wrap it up. We got
to go." And we put him on the
helicopter. We flew him to a Pakistani
military base. They started operating
there and they saved his life. The
doctor told me he had never seen wounds
so severe where the patient lived. And
he lived. He was later taken to a secret
CIA prison where atrocities were
committed against him.
He was tortured mercilessly,
illegally, and moved to six different
black sites in six different countries
before finally ending up in Guantanamo
in 2005.
I've I've reached out over the years a
number of times to his attorneys and I
I've actually become friendly with them
and Abu Zuba and I now exch exchanged
messages
and I apologized to him for what our
country has done to him. This guy was
innocent. He was innocent of everything
that we had accused him of.
But the order was to take him and we
took him and we can't admit that we made
a terrible grievous error.
So think of the technology that we were
using in 2002 to catch somebody who was
supposed to be one of the most dangerous
men in the world. There was almost zero
technology involved.
And fast forward just a number of years
to what you heard in the last
presentation about Vault 7.
I want to tell you I'm I'm going to try
to explain to you how 911 changed the
CIA.
On 9 on 911, the CIA was, you know, an
intelligence service that recruited
spies to steal secrets and analyze those
secrets, etc., etc. on 912. It was a
paramilitary organization,
a paramilitary organization that did not
have to answer to oversight committees
or justice department task forces.
Executive Order 1233, which banned CIA
assassinations, was was amended to not
just allow CIA operations, but to set up
the mechanism by which the CIA could go
all around the world and kill anybody it
wanted.
I sat about 10 feet away from a guy in
the counterterrorism center. Nicest guy.
He'd come in every morning. He'd say,
"Hey guys," we'd say, "Hey, Rick.
Come in on Monday." "Hey guys, how was
your weekend?" "Hey, it was great, Rick.
How about yours?" "Ah, great." "Hey,
having a cookout on Saturday." "Yeah, I
would love to see you, Rick." Finally,
one day, I said to this guy next to me,
I said, "You know, he's the nicest guy
in the world." And I don't I don't even
know what he does here. And he goes,
"John, he's the head of the special
activities division." And I said, 'Oh.
Well, after he left the CIA, there was
an article about him in Vanity Fair of
all places, saying what qualified him to
be the head of the Special Activities
Division was that he had been a hitman
for the Cali cartel when he was
recruited into the CIA right at 911
because we needed somebody who knew how
to kill people and not get caught.
And so he trained an entire cadray that
is now called global services.
With the technology that the CIA has
now,
it is able to carry out a meeting at the
White House every Tuesday morning at
7:00 called the Tuesday morning kill
list meeting.
And what they do is they come up with a
list of people to be executed that week.
And then using technology that we
learned about thanks to the Vault 7
revelations,
global services sends its teams all
around the world. They kill the people
they're supposed to kill and then they
come back for next Tuesday's meeting.
So what kind of technology are we
talking about here? Well, the Vault 7
stuff showed at the very least that
the CIA can take uh possession of your
remotely take possession of your car by
hacking into the into the uh computer
system. Why would they want to take
possession of your car? Maybe to drive
you over a bridge or into an abutment or
into a tree. It's to kill you.
We learned that the CIA can turn a a
smart TV speaker into a into a uh
microphone
and it looks like the TV is still off.
You have no idea that you're being
bugged. Phones, forget it. I've just
given up. When I I used to be on the
board of Wikileaks and
for a while we would just put our phones
in the microwave oven and then have our
have our meeting. And finally somebody
said, "Guys, you know, they still track
us to the meeting. We put our phones in
the microwave. They still know where we
are, even if the phones are in the
microwaves. Then we had to leave our
phones in the hotels and they would
still stop us at the airports on the way
home."
But another thing that we learned too is
that is that NSA I'm sorry, a CIA was
spying on NSA.
Yeah, I actually had to read that twice
when I when I saw it in the Wikileaks
documents. CIA is spying electronically
on NSA.
And then of course the the yet the CIA's
yesmen went on MSNBC that night and
said, "Well, it was probably a training
exercise. We're just trying to prompt
each other to use the best technology."
No. No. The CIA spied on the Senate
Intelligence Committee to see what they
were gathering in their torture report.
So, think of the changes that have taken
place
just between 2002 where all we had was a
camera and a and a cell phone
and now
where what we learned from Vault 7 is
actually old technology.
Is is anybody safe? When the Attorney
General of the United States, Eric
Holder, testifies before the Senate
Armed Services Committee and Senator Ran
Paul says,
"Mr. Attorney General, does the
president have the legal right to murder
an American citizen on US soil without
benefit of a trial?"
And then the eventual answer is yes.
What kind of country do we have?
It's like it's it's gone crazy. But the
technology has moved so quickly that it
has allowed the government to obfuscate
what it's doing and to fudge our own
constitutional protections.
And that's why we need hackers
because hackers are the only people who
are able to keep up with the
intelligence community's hackers. Right?
We all recognize how quickly this stuff
is moving. And so the only way to
counter it is to develop additional
technology to protect Americans to
protect Americans from their own
government.
Thomas Jefferson once said
that periodically the tree of liberty
must be watered with the blood of
martyrs.
I hope that that's not true, but it
seems like we're kind of headed in that
direction.
So when I see things like
news reports that Julian Assange is
working for the Russians, okay, Julian
Assange is a friend of mine. He's been a
friend of mine for 15 years. He's not
working for any Russians. He doesn't
like the Russians any more than than he
likes the Americans. He has no contact
with the Russians ever.
But he's he's a transparency absolutist.
And when we're run by political figures
who are secrecy absolutists,
especially when it pertains to our own
civil rights and civil liberties, then
maybe we need transparency absolutists
to balance the scales.
And so even though I don't understand
99% of what you guys do, um, I'm begging
you to keep doing it because you're the
only thing that stands between us and
authoritarianism today. The CIA is a
rogue organization. So is NSA,
FBI. They're too stupid to be rogue, so
don't worry about them.
Um, but but worry about the CIA and NSA.
You're the only thing that's protecting
us. I'm told I've got like five minutes
for questions. Is that okay?
>> Yeah. You can keep going for a few
minutes and then we can take questions
or we can take questions now.
>> Okay. I I want to say one other thing.
When I first got hired at the CIA, I was
um I was hired to be an analyst in the
office of leadership analysis. It no
longer exists. and I was the classified
bio biographer for Saddam Hussein and
the Iraqi government and I sat next to
the to a guy who did the same thing for
the Iranian government and he was a
techn. Now this was like 1989
1990 so tech was
not what it is today and
our we there was a guy that sat in
between us. We're all within like 8t of
each other. Guy sat in between us was
handling the Saudi royal family. So, he
needed to do a a Saudi royal family
tree.
And the Iran analyst said, "Oh, I'm
really into tech. I can do a program
that'll let you do a family tree." So,
he took two days off. He did this little
program. It made the family tree. The
other analyst populated it. Everybody's
like standing around like, "Oh my god,
look. It's like like this, like the
family tree, and you can see who's
related to whom. Oh my god, they gave
him a $500 exceptional performance
bonus.
Okay, today he is the number four
ranking officer in the CIA. He is the
associate deputy director for
technology.
He's the guy that's liazing with
Palunteer and with INQEL and with with
every one of the defense contractors.
And remember, the CIA's budget is
unlimited.
The day after 911, I walked up to
Kofheer Black, now Ambassador Kofer
Black. He was the director of
counterterrorism. And I said, Kofheer, I
know how busy you are. Again, September
12th, I said, Kofheer, I know how busy
you are, but I have an idea for an
operation that I want to pass by you.
And he put up his hands and he said, I
have so much money, I can't possibly
spend it all. Whatever you want to do,
just do it.
Well, that wasn't just John cuz he liked
John. That was the entire CIA.
So, imagine literally unlimited budgets.
It's a dangerous landscape out there.
And that's why we need people like you
to balance those scales.
Okay. Well, thank you very much and I'm
very happy to answer questions. Thank
you.
If you have questions, please come on up
to the front. Also, an announcement.
We're looking for Valerie Taylor.
Apparently, there is some kind of
emergency. If you could go back
um to the AV section up here in the
back, right? Um great. Thank you, Miss
Taylor. Um come on up with any
questions.
I imagine there's got to be a few. This
was such a compelling story. Thank you
so much.
>> Thank you very much. I appreciate that.
Thank you.
>> Hey, John. Um, so obviously over the
decades we've seen a huge sort of
trickling down of surveillance tools,
technologies, and techniques going from
once, you know, it was just the military
and intelligence and it now is down to
the police. Do you see any parallels in
terms of techniques and technology with
groups like ICE now that they have sort
of more power than before?
>> That's a good question. technology um
similarities between the CIA and other
organizations like law enforcement
organizations like ICE,
those law enforcement organizations,
ICE, DEA, ATF, even BOP, which freaked
me out the other night. I or the other
day I happened to go to Capitol Hill to
see my attorney. He's a friend of mine,
excuse me, as well. we were just going
to go to a baseball game. But I saw this
van load of Bureau of Prisons prison
guards taking off their BOP polo shirts
that say Bureau of Prisons on them and
putting on ATF shirts.
>> And I shouted at them, "Shame on you.
Shame."
But the the kind of surveillance tactics
that they use are very much old school
what the CIA used to do where you know
you've got six cars on a guy and you're
breaking off and coming back on or you
have static surveillance maybe there's
somebody on the second floor of the
Barnes & Noble with binoculars just just
tracking the movement or one of the
things that the French came up with that
the CIA adopted is if you're if you're
confident that you have surveillance,
you're going to have a hard time not
turning around to just see if you're
being followed. So, the French just put
50 people walking toward you. You're not
paying any attention to who's ahead of
you, and then they just break off and go
around, constantly walking toward you,
and you have no idea you're being
surveiled. So, it's a very effective
technique, and that's that's what
they're doing. They're kind of doing
what regular cops do. A lot of sitting
in cars waiting, going to people's
houses or going to the workplaces or
going to places where they may
congregate. You know, guys maybe go to a
bar that they like or they play cards or
whatever. It's very old school. They're
not doing a lot of tech technological
collection. It's too expensive for them.
Their budgets actually are limited, so
it's different.
>> Thank you, John. We have a question from
our virtual attendees from aesthetics.
Why was the CIA able to transform
overnight after 9/11 when government
agencies usually move at such glacial
speeds?
>> I'll give you a two-word answer. Dick
Cheney.
[Laughter]
>> There we go.
>> Seriously,
>> aesthetics has one more for you as well.
Why do you think that none of the
Snowden leaks so far have given anyone
standing to bring lawsuits against the
NSA? You know, I have to say that is an
especially painful issue for me. Um, I
was in prison when Ed Snowden went
public with his revelations and I was
very proud that in a an interview he
gave with the New York Times, he said
that Tom Drake from NSA and I had
inspired him to go public. Um, and he
and I have remained in touch all these
years. And I told him back his dad came
to prison to visit me. And I told Ed
back in 2015,
I guess it was. I said, "The whole
world's going to change because of what
you did." And it didn't. It didn't. It's
like people are like, "Oh, well, if I'm
not breaking the law, then why should I
be worried?" You know who first posed
that? In all seriousness, you know who
first posed that question? If you're not
doing anything wrong, then why are you
worried about it? Who first posed that
question in a public venue? Was Joseph
Gerbles.
Joseph Gerbles asked that question. I
don't want to be in that company.
So yeah, that's that's my biggest
disappointment of the last decade and a
half is that is that things have not
swung the pendulum has not swung to the
other side. I really believed that
eventually there would be enough
pressure on Congress to begin repealing
some of the more egregious parts of the
Patriot Act, for example. And it just
hasn't happened. And for a while,
incrementally,
more and more members of the House would
vote to, you know, repeal and then it
kind of leveled off and fell away. The
last time I talked to Ed, he told me
that he was willing to come home and to
be prosecuted. Uh the uh Justice
Department had made him an offer of 20
years. He said he was willing to do it,
but he wanted permission to stand up in
court and explain why he did what he
did. And DOJ said, "Absolutely not."
And so he didn't come home.
>> Thank you.
>> Terrible. Hi.
>> Hi. Um, there's a very strange large
looking bug that's crawling toward you
over here. Maybe we should speak
directly into the bug over here. I don't
know.
>> Um, over there.
>> Okay. Yeah. Uh,
>> those spotted. We're supposed to kill
those things. Those spotted lantern
flies.
>> So, my question is a little bit of a
difficult one. Maybe. I don't know.
Maybe you have an easy answer for it,
but do you think there's ever any
legitimate case for any government to
have secrets? And where where is that
line drawn if there is?
>> Oh, that's a great question. That's a
very difficult ethical and philosophical
question. I I think the answer is yes,
barely.
For example,
I'm a realist. There are people or
organizations out there who mean us
harm. And it might not be because they
oppose our, you know, Gaza policy, for
example, or our Ukraine policy or
whatever it happens to be, there are
people out there that want to do us
harm. And so if somebody comes to to an
American official and says, "Listen, I
heard this guy talking the other day and
he's planning to put a bomb at the uh
you know McDonald's down the street."
Sure, we want to protect that person's
um uh identity,
but when it comes to
well things like technology, I wouldn't
the world be a better place if we all
shared technology?
you know,
people are racing to go to the moon.
Okay, great. We got a half a dozen
countries going to the moon. What if we
share the technology and we can
actually, you know, develop a program to
mine
meteors or to explore for rare earth
metals on Jupiter or whatever. If we
could share that information rather than
to classify it and keep it from each
other,
I just don't see the reason for all
these classifications.
There's there was a guy named um
oh his name slips in my mind now but
anyway he was the he was the Pentagon's
classification zar under George W. Bush
and now he's an anti-classification
activist an anti-classification
activist. Quite a prominent one. What
the heck is his name? Um it's going to
come to me. He even volunteered to
testify on my behalf, saying that I
should not have been charged in the
first place, that it was improperly
classified. I I don't think what Ed
Snowden revealed should have been
classified.
Remember this, too, and maybe I'm being
a little arrogant about it,
but this information is owned by the
American people, and the American people
have a right to know what the government
is doing in their name, right?
Thank you.
>> We got one. We We only have time for
probably really one or two more
questions here. One coming in from the
virtual environment is do you have any
memories of Krypton?
>> Oh, Crypto. We were just talking about
Krypton the other day, my friends and I.
Um, so Krypton, I was there actually at
the installation.
>> Oh, wow.
>> In December of 1989. So, Krypton is this
large. It's like 7 feet tall and it's an
S-shaped sculpture made out of um out of
iron or bronze maybe. Uh and it it has
letters and words punched in it. But the
word crypto keeps coming up. Krypton
crypto krypton. And it's supposed to be
this like super top secret unbreakable
code. Well, in the '9s
it it became fashionable to try to break
it. the the code guys at the agency and
they actually put the information into a
Cray computer and the Cray computer
couldn't figure it out. So just last
week the the artist who created it
offered to sell
the the the code to the highest bidder
and the money would go to charity. He's
asking like 300 to $500,000.
But we were speculating, my friends and
I were speculating last night that maybe
it's just all [__] He just made it
all up.
>> Cuz right, I mean, we're all trained to
lie for a living. We lie about
everything.
Why would this be any different?
>> Yep. Why not?
Go ahead.
>> Going back to the uh capture of Abu
Zuba, why were the Pakis so
trigger-happy?
>> You think they're trying to sabotage the
operation? Maybe they're secretly
>> We talked about that at length. Were
they trying to sabotage the operation?
Did he know something about Pakistan
that they didn't want him to uh to
reveal? You know, I think at the end of
the day, no. I think this was an one
isolated idiot who thought he could get
promoted by taking out the big man that
he got wrapped up in the excitement. He
had never been in a situation where
bullets were flying before.
You know, there's a famous story about a
guy named um
Bartlett. What's his name? He He's the
guy who killed John Wils Booth and his
orders were very specific. Hudson,
Bartlett Hudson, Bart, something like
that. Uh, very specific. Don't shoot
Booth. Take him alive. Well, he's he
looked threw a knot in in the barn wall
and then he just put his gun up and shot
Booth
because he wanted to be famous. And he
said Jesus came and told him to do it.
That's what he said. And I I always
wondered the same thing about this this
Pakistani guy. He was just a policeman.
He was just supposed to stand there in
like direct traffic and he just opens
fire on these guys on the roof.
So I I I hope it was just a mistake.
>> Can get away with a question. Um hi. Uh,
one of the most interesting things about
your talk to me was the level of detail
that you gave in threat modeling, the
uses of technology for surveillance, the
different uses of different sets of
technology for surveillance, uh, and
different operational methodologies of
the different agencies. One of the
things that I find is very difficult to
explain to activists when running
security trainings, especially
non-technical ones, is how they have to
break down even any individual state
actor into a bunch of sub agencies with
different resourcing. How can we do
better in helping train activists to do
this modeling themselves is one question
and the associated question is a
particular interest right now with the
genocide in Gaza and the US's assistance
for it. What would you recommend as the
most useful thing that US citizens and
hackers in general or the overlap can do
to pressure the United States government
to cease its support for Israel's
genocide?
>> Oh yeah. Wonderful.
Um, to tell you the truth, can can we
chat afterwards because it's it it's
going to be long.
>> Sure.
>> I I appreciate it. Both fantastic
questions. Thank you.
>> Do we
one more real quick?
>> Okay.
>> Hi. Um, yeah. I would like to thank you
for the uh insight that you give into
American intelligence um you know,
operation and mentality. I'm wondering
how would you compare that to uh foreign
intelligence services, their operational
capabilities and their mentality?
>> Yeah, good question. Some are um
exceptional. The Brits are terrific. Uh
the Israelis are terrific only because
there are literally no rules for the
Israelis. They just shoot anybody they
want to shoot and blow up anybody they
want to blow up and then bulldoze your
parents' house and then, you know,
disappear you. So, um, they don't ever
have to worry about testifying before
some congressional committee or
answering to a police investigation.
They just kill everybody. Um, another
thing the Israelis do that we don't do
is um, the Israelis spy on us actively,
oppressively.
Uh, and we are not permitted to spy on
the Israelis. Now, five, the five eyes,
US, UK, Canada, Australia, New Zealand,
we have this agreement where not only do
we not spy on each other, we share
literally everything. We used to have
this classification called secret, no
foreign, releasable, US, UK, Canada,
Australia, New Zealand.
Now, we don't even need that
classification. It's not even a
classification. It's a control. We don't
even need that control anymore because
we share literally everything. We sit
next to them, you know, in our
headquarters, buildings, etc. The
Israelis are are different. We've not
been permitted since the Nixon
administration to spy on Israel. And the
Israelis have literally hundreds of
undeclared spies all over the United
States, mostly at defense contractors
and universities stealing our secrets.
So, you know, when you've got no legal
bars to anything you want to do and
you've got an unlimited budget, yeah,
you can be great. Sure. and then your
your own domestic tech industry is
giving you everything then no problem
and I apologize I've gone over but thank
you very much oh if you're interested in
a surveillance class uh ivyscyber.com
all the uh all the details are there
thank you everybody
[Applause]